<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_odds.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_odds.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>TEI P5 Customization TEST </title>
                <editor xml:id="MT">Magdalena Turska</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>2nd Draft -- 2014-03-22</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Adrian Wisnicki</authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons
                        Attribution 3.0 Unported</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="toc"/>
            <div xml:id="about">
                <head>About This TEST TEI P5 Customization</head>

                <p> This TEI P5 ODD Customization was created by MT </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head>Codicological Description</head>
                <p>The manuscript as it now stands consists of 181 parchment <term type="bla"
                    >folios</term>, plus two <hi>modern</hi> paper flyleaves at each end. Each page is
                    approximately 315 mm x 205 mm. It is bound in a <date notBefore="1800"
                        notAfter="1900">nineteenth-century</date> binding, which is in need of
                    repair, on five medieval sewing-stations.</p>
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head>Quires</head>
                    <p>The manuscript is arranged in twenty-three quires as follows: a singleton
                        (fol. 1), I8 (fols. 2–9), II8 (fols. 10–17), III8 (fols. 18–25), IV8 (fols.
                        26–33), V8 (fols. 34–41), VI8 (fols. 42–49), VII8 (fols. 50–57), VIII8
                        (fols. 58–65), IX8 (fols. 66–73), X8 (fols. 74–81), XI8 (fols. 82–89), XII8
                        (fols. 90–97), XIII8 (fols. 98–105), XIV8 (fols. 106–13), XV8 (fols.
                        114–21), XVI8 (fols. 122–29), XVII8 (fols. 130–37), XVIII8 (fols. 138–45),
                        XIX8 (fols. 146–53), XX8 (fols. 154–61), XXI4 (fols. 162–65), XXII8 (fols.
                        166–73), XXIII8 (fols. 174–81). In short, the manuscript consists entirely
                        of regular quires of eight, with two small exceptions: it starts with a
                        singleton, and the twenty-first quire is a quire of only four leaves, two
                        bifolia. M. R. James thought that the first quire had once contained five
                        sheets, making ten leaves, and that the pair to fol. 1, which would have
                        come between fols. 9 and 10, had been excised. I think it more likely, given
                        the regularity of the rest of the manuscript and the fact that no text is
                        missing between fols. 9 and 10, that fol. 1 was added to the manuscript in
                        the mid-twelfth century to enlarge the blank space available for the
                        addition of historical material. (On this added historical material, see
                        below.) James suggests that the note on 1r is only the end of a longer text;
                        if this were true, fol. 1 would be the last leaf of an added quire. </p>
                    <p>The sheets within the quires are almost without exception arranged HFFH, so
                        that within each opening either both verso and recto are the hair side of
                        the parchment or both are the flesh side. This was good practice in medieval
                        book production because the hair side of the parchment was usually darker
                        than the flesh side and showed follicles, while the flesh side might be
                        greasier and have vein patterning. (Early Insular techniques of parchment
                        preparation, however, rendered this arrangement unnecessary by producing a
                        hair and flesh side which were very difficult to tell apart.) The parchment
                        in Pembroke 25 is of a practical quality, rather than being highly prepared.
                        It is quite stiff; the hair-side is yellow-brown with clearly visible
                        follicles; the flesh-side is paler and often shows a pattern of veining
                        (image), typically caused by inadequate draining of blood from the animal’s
                        body at slaughter, leaving a residue of iron to react with chemicals used
                        later in the parchmenting process. Some folios, made from the edge of the
                        skin, lack their lower corners. Many slits, tears, or holes in the parchment
                        have been mended with chamfered patches or sewing, sometimes in colored
                        thread. The impression left is of a workmanlike book, not high-status, but
                        practical in its construction. </p>
                    <p>The one exception to the arrangement of hair facing hair and flesh facing
                        flesh occurs in the thirteenth quire, where the second sheet of the quire,
                        fols. 99 and 104, is arranged with hair outwards instead of inwards. This
                        means that in the openings of 98v–99r, 99v–100r, 103v–104r, and 104v–105r,
                        hair faces flesh or vice versa. However, in this quire the hair and flesh
                        sides of the parchment are much more alike than elsewhere in the book, and
                        the contrast in the openings is hardly noticeable. This similarity
                        presumably led to a mistake by the scribe. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head>Ruling</head>
                    <p>The manuscript is written in a single column, fols. 1–165 in 28 lines, and
                        fols. 166–73 in 27 lines. 174r was ruled for 28 lines, but only 27 were
                        written, and from 175r to the end of the manuscript there are 27 ruled lines
                        per page. These were ruled drypoint before the parchment was folded. The
                        prickings in the outer margin seem to have been made with a triangular
                        point. The size of the writing area is approximately 250 x 145 mm, with 9–10
                        mm between ruled lines, and with a double vertical bounding line ruled to
                        provide space for litterae notabiliores. On occasion the gap between lines
                        is not regular, for example on fol. 180.</p>
                    <p>paragrah</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subsection">
                    <head>Ink</head>
                    <p>The ink is shiny and black; this is more typical of the Anglo-Saxon than the
                        Continental tradition at this time. Litterae notabiliores have been picked
                        out in red (image). </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head>Marks of provenance</head>
                <p>The manuscript contains several marks of provenance assigning it to Bury St
                    Edmunds abbey in Suffolk.</p>

            </div>


        </body>
        <back>

            <div>
                <head>Formal declaration and Reference Pages</head>
                <!-- If you add or delete elements, modify the specList above and the documentation -->
                test of markdown </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
